<XML><RECORDS>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>1</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>1000 Genomes Project Consortium, </AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2012</YEAR><DATE>November</DATE><TITLE>An integrated map of genetic variation from 1,092 human genomes.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>491</VOLUME><NUMBER>7422</NUMBER><PAGES>56-65</PAGES><LABEL>1KG2012</LABEL><URL>10.1038/nature11632</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature11632</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>5</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>2</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Abuzaid, Firas</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bradley, Joseph K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Liang, Feynman T</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Feng, Andrew</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yang, Lee</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zaharia, Matei</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Talwalkar, Ameet S</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2016</YEAR><TITLE>Yggdrasil: An Optimized System for Training Deep Decision Trees at Scale</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 29</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Curran Associates, Inc.</PUBLISHER><PAGES>3817-3825</PAGES><LABEL>NIPS2016_6366</LABEL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://papers.nips.cc/paper/6366-yggdrasil-an-optimized-system-for-training-deep-decision-trees-at-scale.pdf</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>16</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>3</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Apache Software Foundation, </AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2016</YEAR><DATE>October</DATE><TITLE>Spark Overview</TITLE><LABEL>Spark.2016</LABEL><NOTES>accessed on Thursday, October 27, 2016</NOTES><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://spark.apache.org/docs/latest/mllib-ensembles.html</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>4</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Bauer, Denis C.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gaff, Clara</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dinger, Marcel E.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Caramins, Melody</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Buske, Fabian A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Fenech, Michael</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hansen, David</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cobiac, Lynne</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2014</YEAR><DATE>September</DATE><TITLE>Genomics and personalised whole-of-life healthcare.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Trends in Molecular Medicine</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>CSIRO Preventative Health National Research Flagship, Adelaide, SA 5000, Australia.</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>20</VOLUME><NUMBER>9</NUMBER><PAGES>479-486</PAGES><LABEL>Bauer2014</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Genome sequencing has the potential for stratified cancer treatment and improved diagnostics for rare disorders. However, sequencing needs to be utilised in risk stratification on a population scale to deepen the impact on the health system by addressing common diseases, where individual genomic variants have variable penetrance and minor impact. As the accuracy of genomic risk predictors is bounded by heritability, environmental factors such as diet, lifestyle, and microbiome have to be considered. Large-scale, longitudinal research programmes need to study the intrinsic properties between both genetics and environment to unravel their risk contribution. During this discovery process, frameworks need to be established to counteract unrealistic expectations. Sufficient scientific evidence is needed to interpret sources of uncertainty and inform decision making for clinical management and personal health.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1016/j.molmed.2014.04.001</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molmed.2014.04.001</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>1</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>5</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Bellman, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bellman, R.E.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>1961</YEAR><TITLE>Adaptive Control Processes: A Guided Tour</TITLE><PUBLISHER>Princeton University Press</PUBLISHER><ALTERNATE_TITLE>Princeton Legacy Library</ALTERNATE_TITLE><LABEL>bellman1961adaptive</LABEL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>https://books.google.com.au/books?id=POAmAAAAMAAJ</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>6</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Biau, G&#x00E9;rard</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2012</YEAR><DATE>April</DATE><TITLE>Analysis of a Random Forests Model</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Journal of Machine Learning Research</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>JMLR.org</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>13</VOLUME><NUMBER>1</NUMBER><PAGES>1063-1095</PAGES><ISBN>1532-4435</ISBN><LABEL>Biau.2012</LABEL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2503308.2343682</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>7</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Breiman, Leo</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2001</YEAR><DATE>October</DATE><TITLE>Random Forests</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Machine Learning</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>45</VOLUME><NUMBER>1</NUMBER><PAGES>5-32</PAGES><LABEL>Breiman2001</LABEL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1010933404324</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>8</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Bressler, Ryan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kreisberg, Richard B.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bernard, Brady</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Niederhuber, John E.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Vockley, Joseph G.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Shmulevich, Ilya</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Knijnenburg, Theo A.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2015</YEAR><TITLE>CloudForest: A Scalable and Efficient Random Forest Implementation for Biological Data.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>PLoS One</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Institute for Systems Biology, Seattle, WA, United States of America.</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>10</VOLUME><NUMBER>12</NUMBER><PAGES>e0144820</PAGES><LABEL>Bressler2015</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Random Forest has become a standard data analysis tool in computational biology. However, extensions to existing implementations are often necessary to handle the complexity of biological datasets and their associated research questions. The growing size of these datasets requires high performance implementations. We describe CloudForest, a Random Forest package written in Go, which is particularly well suited for large, heterogeneous, genetic and biomedical datasets. CloudForest includes several extensions, such as dealing with unbalanced classes and missing values. Its flexible design enables users to easily implement additional extensions. CloudForest achieves fast running times by effective use of the CPU cache, optimizing for different classes of features and efficiently multi-threading. https://github.com/ilyalab/CloudForest.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1371/journal.pone.0144820</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0144820</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>9</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Chen, Xi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ishwaran, Hemant</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2012</YEAR><TITLE>Random forests for genomic data analysis</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Genomics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>99</VOLUME><NUMBER>6</NUMBER><PAGES>323-329</PAGES><ISBN>0888-7543</ISBN><LABEL>Chen.and.Ishwaran.2012</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Random forests (RF) is a popular tree-based ensemble machine learning tool that is highly data adaptive, applies to large p, small n problems, and is able to account for correlation as well as interactions among features. This makes \RF\ particularly appealing for high-dimensional genomic data analysis. In this article, we systematically review the applications and recent progresses of \RF\ for genomic data, including prediction and classification, variable selection, pathway analysis, genetic association and epistasis detection, and unsupervised learning. </ABSTRACT><URL>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ygeno.2012.04.003</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0888754312000626</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>10</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Consortium, Wellcome Trust Case Control</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2007</YEAR><DATE>June</DATE><TITLE>Genome-wide association study of 14,000 cases of seven common diseases and 3,000 shared controls.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>447</VOLUME><NUMBER>7145</NUMBER><PAGES>661-678</PAGES><LABEL>CCC2007</LABEL><URL>10.1038/nature05911</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature05911</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>11</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Cutler, D. Richard</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Edwards Jr., Thomas C.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Beard, Karen H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cutler, Adele</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hess, Kyle T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gibson, Jacob</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lawler, Joshua J.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2007</YEAR><TITLE>Random forest for classification in ecology</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Ecology</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>88</VOLUME><NUMBER>11</NUMBER><PAGES>2783-2792</PAGES><LABEL>Cutler.at.al.2007</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Classification procedures are some of the most widely used statistical methods in ecology. Random forests (RF) is a new and powerful statistical classifier that is well established in other disciplines but is relatively unknown in ecology. Advantages of RF compared to other statistical classifiers include (1) very high classification accuracy; (2) a novel method of determining variable importance; (3) ability to model complex interactions among predictor variables; (4) flexibility to perform several types of statistical data analysis, including regression, classification, survival analysis, and unsupervised learning; and (5) an algorithm for imputing missing values. We compared the accuracies of RF and four other commonly used statistical classifiers using data on invasive plant species presence in Lava Beds National Monument, California, USA, rare lichen species presence in the Pacific Northwest, USA, and nest sites for cavity nesting birds in the Uinta Mountains, Utah, USA. We observed high classification accuracy in all applications as measured by cross-validation and, in the case of the lichen data, by independent test data, when comparing RF to other common classification methods. We also observed that the variables that RF identified as most important for classifying invasive plant species coincided with expectations based on the literature.</ABSTRACT></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>12</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>D\'iaz-Uriarte, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Alvar\'ez de Andres, S.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2006</YEAR><TITLE>Gene selection and classification of microarray data using random forest</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>BMC Bioinformatics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>7</VOLUME><PAGES>3</PAGES><LABEL>Diaz.and.Alvarez.2006</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Selection of relevant genes for sample classification is a common task in most gene expression studies, where researchers try to identify the smallest possible set of genes that can still achieve good predictive performance (for instance, for future use with diagnostic purposes in clinical practice). Many gene selection approaches use univariate (gene-by-gene) rankings of gene relevance and arbitrary thresholds to select the number of genes, can only be applied to two-class problems, and use gene selection ranking criteria unrelated to the classification algorithm. In contrast, random forest is a classification algorithm well suited for microarray data: it shows excellent performance even when most predictive variables are noise, can be used when the number of variables is much larger than the number of observations and in problems involving more than two classes, and returns measures of variable importance. Thus, it is important to understand the performance of random forest with microarray data and its possible use for gene selection.\ We investigate the use of random forest for classification of microarray data (including multi-class problems) and propose a new method of gene selection in classification problems based on random forest. Using simulated and nine microarray data sets we show that random forest has comparable performance to other classification methods, including DLDA, KNN, and SVM, and that the new gene selection procedure yields very small sets of genes (often smaller than alternative methods) while preserving predictive accuracy.\ Because of its performance and features, random forest and gene selection using random forest should probably become part of the "standard tool-box" of methods for class prediction and gene selection with microarray data.</ABSTRACT><NOTES>[PubMed Central:\hrefhttp://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1363357PMC1363357] [DOI:\hrefhttp://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-7-310.1186/1471-2105-7-3] [PubMed:\hrefhttp://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1639892616398926]</NOTES></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>16</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>13</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Dietterich, Thomas G.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2002</YEAR><DATE>September</DATE><TITLE>Bias-Variance Analysis of Ensemble Learning</TITLE><LABEL>Dietterich.2002</LABEL><NOTES>Lecture presented at the IIASS International School on Neural Nets "E.R. Caianiello" 7th Course, Ensemble Methods for Learning Machines</NOTES><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://www.cs.orst.edu1 tgd/talks/BV.ppt</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>14</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Dixon, Anna L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Liang, Liming</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Moffatt, Miriam F</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chen, Wei</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Heath, Simon</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wong, Kenny C C</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Taylor, Jenny</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Burnett, Edward</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gut, Ivo</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Farrall, Martin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>al. , et</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2007</YEAR><DATE>Sep</DATE><TITLE>A genome-wide association study of global gene expression</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature Genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Springer Nature</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>39</VOLUME><NUMBER>10</NUMBER><PAGES>1202‚Äì1207</PAGES><ISBN>1061-4036</ISBN><LABEL>Dixon2007</LABEL><URL>10.1038/ng2109</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng2109</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>47</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>15</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Donoho, David</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Stodden, Victoria</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2006</YEAR><TITLE>Breakdown point of model selection when the number of variables exceeds the number of observations</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>The 2006 IEEE International Joint Conference on Neural Network Proceedings</SECONDARY_TITLE><PAGES>1916-1921</PAGES><LABEL>Donoho.and.Stodden.2006</LABEL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>16</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Donoho, David</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanner, Jared</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2009</YEAR><TITLE>Observed universality of phase transitions in high-dimensional geometry, with implications for modern data analysis and signal processing</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>The Royal Society</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>367</VOLUME><NUMBER>1906</NUMBER><PAGES>4273-4293</PAGES><ISBN>1364-503X</ISBN><LABEL>Donoho.and.Tanner.2009</LABEL><ABSTRACT>We review connections between phase transitions in high-dimensional combinatorial geometry and phase transitions occurring in modern high-dimensional data analysis and signal processing. In data analysis, such transitions arise as abrupt breakdown of linear model selection, robust data fitting or compressed sensing reconstructions, when the complexity of the model or the number of outliers increases beyond a threshold. In combinatorial geometry, these transitions appear as abrupt changes in the properties of face counts of convex polytopes when the dimensions are varied. The thresholds in these very different problems appear in the same critical locations after appropriate calibration of variables. These thresholds are important in each subject area: for linear modelling, they place hard limits on the degree to which the now ubiquitous high-throughput data analysis can be successful; for robustness, they place hard limits on the degree to which standard robust fitting methods can tolerate outliers before breaking down; for compressed sensing, they define the sharp boundary of the undersampling/sparsity trade-off curve in undersampling theorems. Existing derivations of phase transitions in combinatorial geometry assume that the underlying matrices have independent and identically distributed Gaussian elements. In applications, however, it often seems that Gaussianity is not required. We conducted an extensive computational experiment and formal inferential analysis to test the hypothesis that these phase transitions are universal across a range of underlying matrix ensembles. We ran millions of linear programs using random matrices spanning several matrix ensembles and problem sizes; visually, the empirical phase transitions do not depend on the ensemble, and they agree extremely well with the asymptotic theory assuming Gaussianity. Careful statistical analysis reveals discrepancies that can be explained as transient terms, decaying with problem size. The experimental results are thus consistent with an asymptotic large-n universality across matrix ensembles; finite-sample universality can be rejected. \textcopyright 2009 The Royal Society</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1098/rsta.2009.0152</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://rsta.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/367/1906/4273</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>17</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Duncan, Emma L.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Danoy, Patrick</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kemp, John P.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Leo, Paul J.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>McCloskey, Eugene</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nicholson, Geoffrey C.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eastell, Richard</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Prince, Richard L.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eisman, John A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jones, Graeme</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sambrook, Philip N.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Reid, Ian R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dennison, Elaine M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wark, John</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Richards, J. Brent</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Uitterlinden, Andre G.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Spector, Tim D.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Esapa, Chris</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cox, Roger D.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Brown, Steve D. M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Thakker, Rajesh V.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Addison, Kathryn A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bradbury, Linda A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Center, Jacqueline R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cooper, Cyrus</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cremin, Catherine</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Estrada, Karol</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Felsenberg, Dieter</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gl√ºer, Claus-C.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hadler, Johanna</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Henry, Margaret J.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hofman, Albert</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kotowicz, Mark A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Makovey, Joanna</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nguyen, Sing C.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nguyen, Tuan V.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pasco, Julie A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pryce, Karena</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Reid, David M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rivadeneira, Fernando</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Roux, Christian</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Stefansson, Kari</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Styrkarsdottir, Unnur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Thorleifsson, Gudmar</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tichawangana, Rumbidzai</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Evans, David M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Brown, Matthew A.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2011</YEAR><DATE>April</DATE><TITLE>Genome-Wide Association Study Using Extreme Truncate Selection Identifies Novel Genes Affecting Bone Mineral Density and Fracture Risk</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>PLoS Genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Public Library of Science</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>7</VOLUME><NUMBER>4</NUMBER><PAGES>1-10</PAGES><LABEL>Duncan.2011</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Author Summary Osteoporotic fracture is a major cause of early mortality and morbidity in the community. To identify genes associated with osteoporosis, we have performed a genome-wide association study. In order to improve study power and to address the demographic group of highest risk from osteoporotic fracture, we have used a unique study design, studying 1,955 postmenopausal women with either extreme high or low hip bone mineral density. We then confirmed our findings in 20,898 women from the general population. Our study replicated 21 of 26 known osteoporosis genes, and it identified a further six novel loci (in or nearby CLCN7, GALNT3, IBSP, LTBP3, RSPO3, and SOX4). For one of these loci, GALTN3, we demonstrate in a mouse model that a loss-of-function genetic mutation in GALNT3 causes high bone mass. These findings report novel mechanisms by which osteoporosis can arise, and they significantly add to our understanding of the aetiology of the disease.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1371/journal.pgen.1001372</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1371%2Fjournal.pgen.1001372</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>18</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Foley, Samantha B.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rios, Jonathan J.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mgbemena, Victoria E.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Robinson, Linda S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hampel, Heather L.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Toland, Amanda E.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Durham, Leslie</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ross, Theodora S.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2015</YEAR><DATE>January</DATE><TITLE>Use of Whole Genome Sequencing for Diagnosis and Discovery in the Cancer Genetics Clinic</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>EBioMedicine</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Elsevier BV</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>2</VOLUME><NUMBER>1</NUMBER><PAGES>74-81</PAGES><ISBN>2352-3964</ISBN><LABEL>Foley2015</LABEL><URL>10.1016/j.ebiom.2014.12.003</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2014.12.003</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>19</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Friedman, Jerome H.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>1997</YEAR><TITLE>On Bias, Variance, 0/1--Loss, and the Curse-of-Dimensionality</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>1</VOLUME><NUMBER>1</NUMBER><PAGES>55-77</PAGES><ISBN>1573-756X</ISBN><LABEL>Friedman.1997</LABEL><ABSTRACT>The classification problem is considered in which an outputvariable y assumes discrete values with respectiveprobabilities that depend upon the simultaneous values of a set of input variables x = \x\_1,....,x\_n\. At issue is how error in the estimates of theseprobabilities affects classification error when the estimates are used ina classification rule. These effects are seen to be somewhat counterintuitive in both their strength and nature. In particular the bias andvariance components of the estimation error combine to influenceclassification in a very different way than with squared error on theprobabilities themselves. Certain types of (very high) bias can becanceled by low variance to produce accurate classification. This candramatically mitigate the effect of the bias associated with some simpleestimators like ``naive'' Bayes, and the bias induced by thecurse-of-dimensionality on nearest-neighbor procedures. This helps explainwhy such simple methods are often competitive with and sometimes superiorto more sophisticated ones for classification, and why``bagging/aggregating'' classifiers can often improveaccuracy. These results also suggest simple modifications to theseprocedures that can (sometimes dramatically) further improve theirclassification performance.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1023/A:1009778005914</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1009778005914</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>20</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Genuer, Robin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Poggi, Jean-Michel</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tuleau-Malot, Christine</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2010</YEAR><DATE>October</DATE><TITLE>Variable Selection Using Random Forests</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Pattern Recognition Letters</SECONDARY_TITLE><PLACE_PUBLISHED>New York, NY, USA</PLACE_PUBLISHED><PUBLISHER>Elsevier Science Inc.</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>31</VOLUME><NUMBER>14</NUMBER><PAGES>2225-2236</PAGES><ISBN>0167-8655</ISBN><LABEL>Genuer.et.al.2010</LABEL><URL>10.1016/j.patrec.2010.03.014</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.patrec.2010.03.014</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>21</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Goldstein, B. A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Polley, E. C.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Briggs, F. B.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2011</YEAR><TITLE>Random forests for genetic association studies</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Statistical Applications in Genetics and Molecular Biology</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>10</VOLUME><NUMBER>1</NUMBER><PAGES>32</PAGES><LABEL>Goldstein.et.al.2011</LABEL><ABSTRACT>The Random Forests (RF) algorithm has become a commonly used machine learning algorithm for genetic association studies. It is well suited for genetic applications since it is both computationally efficient and models genetic causal mechanisms well. With its growing ubiquity, there has been inconsistent and less than optimal use of RF in the literature. The purpose of this review is to breakdown the theoretical and statistical basis of RF so that practitioners are able to apply it in their work. An emphasis is placed on showing how the various components contribute to bias and variance, as well as discussing variable importance measures. Applications specific to genetic studies are highlighted. To provide context, RF is compared to other commonly used machine learning algorithms.</ABSTRACT><NOTES>[PubMed Central:\hrefhttp://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3154091PMC3154091] [DOI:\hrefhttp://dx.doi.org/10.2202/1544-6115.169110.2202/1544-6115.1691] [PubMed:\hrefhttp://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2288987622889876]</NOTES></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>22</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Ho, Tin Kam</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2002</YEAR><TITLE>A Data Complexity Analysis of Comparative Advantages of Decision Forest Constructors</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Pattern Analysis &#x0026; Applications</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>5</VOLUME><NUMBER>2</NUMBER><PAGES>102-112</PAGES><ISBN>1433-7541</ISBN><LABEL>Ho.2002</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Using a number of measures for characterising the complexity of classification problems, we studied the comparative advantages of two methods for constructing decision forests - bootstrapping and random subspaces. We investigated a collection of 392 two-class problems from the UCI depository, and observed that there are strong correlations between the classifier accuracies and measures of length of class boundaries, thickness of the class manifolds, and nonlinearities of decision boundaries. We found characteristics of both difficult and easy cases where combination methods are no better than single classifiers. Also, we observed that the bootstrapping method is better when the training samples are sparse, and the subspace method is better when the classes are compact and the boundaries are smooth.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1007/s100440200009</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s100440200009</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>23</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Hothorn, Torsten</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hornik, Kurt</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zeileis, Achim</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2006</YEAR><DATE>September</DATE><TITLE>Unbiased Recursive Partitioning: A Conditional Inference Framework</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Informa UK Limited</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>15</VOLUME><NUMBER>3</NUMBER><PAGES>651-674</PAGES><ISBN>1537-2715</ISBN><LABEL>Hothorn2006</LABEL><URL>10.1198/106186006x133933</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1198/106186006X133933</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>24</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Howie, Bryan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Fuchsberger, Christian</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Stephens, Matthew</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Marchini, Jonathan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Abecasis, Gon\ccalo R.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2012</YEAR><DATE>August</DATE><TITLE>Fast and accurate genotype imputation in genome-wide association studies through pre-phasing.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature Genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Department of Human Genetics, University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois, USA.</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>44</VOLUME><NUMBER>8</NUMBER><PAGES>955-959</PAGES><LABEL>Howie2012</LABEL><ABSTRACT>The 1000 Genomes Project and disease-specific sequencing efforts are producing large collections of haplotypes that can be used as reference panels for genotype imputation in genome-wide association studies (GWAS). However, imputing from large reference panels with existing methods imposes a high computational burden. We introduce a strategy called 'pre-phasing' that maintains the accuracy of leading methods while reducing computational costs. We first statistically estimate the haplotypes for each individual within the GWAS sample (pre-phasing) and then impute missing genotypes into these estimated haplotypes. This reduces the computational cost because (i) the GWAS samples must be phased only once, whereas standard methods would implicitly repeat phasing with each reference panel update, and (ii) it is much faster to match a phased GWAS haplotype to one reference haplotype than to match two unphased GWAS genotypes to a pair of reference haplotypes. We implemented our approach in the MaCH and IMPUTE2 frameworks, and we tested it on data sets from the Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium 2 (WTCCC2), the Genetic Association Information Network (GAIN), the Women's Health Initiative (WHI) and the 1000 Genomes Project. This strategy will be particularly valuable for repeated imputation as reference panels evolve.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1038/ng.2354</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.2354</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>25</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Kemp, John P.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Medina-Gomez, Carolina</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Estrada, Karol</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>St Pourcain, Beate</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Heppe, Denise H. M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Warrington, Nicole M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Oei, Ling</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ring, Susan M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kruithof, Claudia J.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Timpson, Nicholas J.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wolber, Lisa E.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Reppe, Sjur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gautvik, Kaare</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Grundberg, Elin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ge, Bing</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van der Eerden, Bram</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van de Peppel, Jeroen</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hibbs, Matthew A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ackert-Bicknell, Cheryl L.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Choi, Kwangbom</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Koller, Daniel L.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Econs, Michael J.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Williams, Frances M. K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Foroud, Tatiana</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Carola Zillikens, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohlsson, Claes</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hofman, Albert</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Uitterlinden, Andr√© G.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Davey Smith, George</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jaddoe, Vincent W. V.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tobias, Jonathan H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rivadeneira, Fernando</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Evans, David M.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2014</YEAR><DATE>April</DATE><TITLE>Phenotypic Dissection of Bone Mineral Density Reveals Skeletal Site Specificity and Facilitates the Identification of Novel Loci in the Genetic Regulation of Bone Mass Attainment</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>PLoS Genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><PLACE_PUBLISHED>San Francisco, USA</PLACE_PUBLISHED><PUBLISHER>Public Library of Science</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>10</VOLUME><NUMBER>6</NUMBER><PAGES>e1004423</PAGES><ISBN>1553-7404</ISBN><LABEL>Kemp2014</LABEL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4063697/</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>26</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Li, Li</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cheng, Wei-Yi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Glicksberg, Benjamin S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gottesman, Omri</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tamler, Ronald</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chen, Rong</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bottinger, Erwin P.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dudley, Joel T.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2015</YEAR><DATE>October</DATE><TITLE>Identification of type 2 diabetes subgroups through topological analysis of patient similarity.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Science Translational Medicine</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Department of Genetics and Genomic Sciences, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, 700 Lexington Ave., New York, NY 10065, USA. Department of Health Policy and Research, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, NY 10029, USA. joel.dudley@mssm.edu.</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>7</VOLUME><NUMBER>311</NUMBER><PAGES>311ra174</PAGES><LABEL>Li2015</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Type 2 diabetes (T2D) is a heterogeneous complex disease affecting more than 29 million Americans alone with a rising prevalence trending toward steady increases in the coming decades. Thus, there is a pressing clinical need to improve early prevention and clinical management of T2D and its complications. Clinicians have understood that patients who carry the T2D diagnosis have a variety of phenotypes and susceptibilities to diabetes-related complications. We used a precision medicine approach to characterize the complexity of T2D patient populations based on high-dimensional electronic medical records (EMRs) and genotype data from 11,210 individuals. We successfully identified three distinct subgroups of T2D from topology-based patient-patient networks. Subtype 1 was characterized by T2D complications diabetic nephropathy and diabetic retinopathy; subtype 2 was enriched for cancer malignancy and cardiovascular diseases; and subtype 3 was associated most strongly with cardiovascular diseases, neurological diseases, allergies, and HIV infections. We performed a genetic association analysis of the emergent T2D subtypes to identify subtype-specific genetic markers and identified 1279, 1227, and 1338 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) that mapped to 425, 322, and 437 unique genes specific to subtypes 1, 2, and 3, respectively. By assessing the human disease-SNP association for each subtype, the enriched phenotypes and biological functions at the gene level for each subtype matched with the disease comorbidities and clinical differences that we identified through EMRs. Our approach demonstrates the utility of applying the precision medicine paradigm in T2D and the promise of extending the approach to the study of other complex, multifactorial diseases.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1126/scitranslmed.aaa9364</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.aaa9364</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>27</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Liaw, Andy</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wiener, Matthew</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2002</YEAR><TITLE>Classification and Regression by randomForest</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>R News</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>2</VOLUME><NUMBER>3</NUMBER><PAGES>18-22</PAGES><LABEL>Liaw.and.Weiner.2002</LABEL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://CRAN.R-project.org/doc/Rnews/</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>28</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Liu, Yao-Zhong</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wilson, Scott G.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wang, Liang</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Liu, Xiao-Gang</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Guo, Yan-Fang</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Li, Jian</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yan, Han</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Deloukas, Panos</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Soranzo, Nicole</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chinnapen-Horsley, Usha</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cervino, Alesandra</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Williams, Frances M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Xiong, Dong-Hai</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhang, Yin-Ping</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jin, Tian-Bo</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Levy, Shawn</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Papasian, Christopher J.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Drees, Betty M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hamilton, James J.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Recker, Robert R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Spector, Tim D.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Deng, Hong-Wen</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2008</YEAR><DATE>September</DATE><TITLE>Identification of PLCL1 Gene for Hip Bone Size Variation in Females in a Genome-Wide Association Study</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>PLoS One</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Public Library of Science</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>3</VOLUME><NUMBER>9</NUMBER><PAGES>1-10</PAGES><LABEL>Liu2008</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Osteoporosis, the most prevalent metabolic bone disease among older people, increases risk for low trauma hip fractures (HF) that are associated with high morbidity and mortality. Hip bone size (BS) has been identified as one of the key measurable risk factors for HF. Although hip BS is highly genetically determined, genetic factors underlying the trait are still poorly defined. Here, we performed the first genome-wide association study (GWAS) of hip BS interrogating ‚àº380,000 SNPs on the Affymetrix platform in 1,000 homogeneous unrelated Caucasian subjects, including 501 females and 499 males. We identified a gene, PLCL1 (phospholipase c-like 1), that had four SNPs associated with hip BS at, or approaching, a genome-wide significance level in our female subjects; the most significant SNP, rs7595412, achieved a p value of 3.72√ó10‚àí7. The gene's importance to hip BS was replicated using the Illumina genotyping platform in an independent UK cohort containing 1,216 Caucasian females. Two SNPs of the PLCL1 gene, rs892515 and rs9789480, surrounded by the four SNPs identified in our GWAS, achieved p values of 8.62√ó10‚àí3 and 2.44√ó10‚àí3, respectively, for association with hip BS. Imputation analyses on our GWAS and the UK samples further confirmed the replication signals; eight SNPs of the gene achieved combined imputed p values&#x3c;10‚àí5 in the two samples. The PLCL1 gene's relevance to HF was also observed in a Chinese sample containing 403 females, including 266 with HF and 177 control subjects. A SNP of the PLCL1 gene, rs3771362 that is only ‚àº0.6 kb apart from the most significant SNP detected in our GWAS (rs7595412), achieved a p value of 7.66√ó10‚àí3 (odds ratio = 0.26) for association with HF. Additional biological support for the role of PLCL1 in BS comes from previous demonstrations that the PLCL1 protein inhibits IP3 (inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate)-mediated calcium signaling, an important pathway regulating mechanical sensing of bone cells. Our findings suggest that PLCL1 is a novel gene associated with variation in hip BS, and provide new insights into the pathogenesis of HF.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1371/journal.pone.0003160</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0003160</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>29</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Loebbecke, Claudia</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Picot, Arnold</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2015</YEAR><DATE>September</DATE><TITLE>Reflections on societal and business model transformation arising from digitization and big data analytics: A research agenda</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>The Journal of Strategic Information Systems</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Elsevier BV</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>24</VOLUME><NUMBER>3</NUMBER><PAGES>149-157</PAGES><ISBN>0963-8687</ISBN><LABEL>Loebbecke2015</LABEL><URL>10.1016/j.jsis.2015.08.002</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jsis.2015.08.002</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>30</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Magali, Saint Martin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Labeix, Pierre</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Garet, Martin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Thomas, Thierry</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Barth√©l√©my, Jean-Claude</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Collet, Philippe</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Roche, Fr√©d√©ric</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sforza, Emilia</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2016</YEAR><DATE>Nov</DATE><TITLE>Does Subjective Sleep Affect Bone Mineral Density in Older People with Minimal Health Disorders? The PROOF Cohort</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Journal of Clinical Sleep Medicine</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM)</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>12</VOLUME><NUMBER>11</NUMBER><PAGES>1461‚Äì1469</PAGES><ISBN>1550-9397</ISBN><LABEL>Magali2016</LABEL><URL>10.5664/jcsm.6266</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.5664/jcsm.6266</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>31</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Manolio, Teri A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Collins, Francis S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cox, Nancy J.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Goldstein, David B.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hindorff, Lucia A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hunter, David J.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>McCarthy, Mark I.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ramos, Erin M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cardon, Lon R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chakravarti, Aravinda</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cho, Judy H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Guttmacher, Alan E.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kong, Augustine</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kruglyak, Leonid</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mardis, Elaine</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rotimi, Charles N.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Slatkin, Montgomery</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Valle, David</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Whittemore, Alice S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Boehnke, Michael</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Clark, Andrew G.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eichler, Evan E.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gibson, Greg</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Haines, Jonathan L.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mackay, Trudy F C.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>McCarroll, Steven A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Visscher, Peter M.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2009</YEAR><DATE>October</DATE><TITLE>Finding the missing heritability of complex diseases.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>National Human Genome Research Institute, Building 31, Room 4B09, 31 Center Drive, MSC 2152, Bethesda, Maryland 20892-2152, USA. manoliot@mail.nih.gov</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>461</VOLUME><NUMBER>7265</NUMBER><PAGES>747-753</PAGES><LABEL>Manolio2009</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Genome-wide association studies have identified hundreds of genetic variants associated with complex human diseases and traits, and have provided valuable insights into their genetic architecture. Most variants identified so far confer relatively small increments in risk, and explain only a small proportion of familial clustering, leading many to question how the remaining, 'missing' heritability can be explained. Here we examine potential sources of missing heritability and propose research strategies, including and extending beyond current genome-wide association approaches, to illuminate the genetics of complex diseases and enhance its potential to enable effective disease prevention or treatment.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1038/nature08494</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature08494</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>32</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Nicod, J√©r√¥me</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Davies, Robert W</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cai, Na</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hassett, Carl</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Goodstadt, Leo</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cosgrove, Cormac</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yee, Benjamin K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lionikaite, Vikte</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>McIntyre, Rebecca E</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Remme, Carol Ann</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>al. , et</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2016</YEAR><DATE>Jul</DATE><TITLE>Genome-wide association of multiple complex traits in outbred mice by ultra-low-coverage sequencing</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature Genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Springer Nature</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>48</VOLUME><NUMBER>8</NUMBER><PAGES>912‚Äì918</PAGES><ISBN>1546-1718</ISBN><LABEL>Nicod2016</LABEL><URL>10.1038/ng.3595</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.3595</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>33</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>O'Brien, Aidan R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Saunders, Neil F. W.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Guo, Yi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Buske, Fabian A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Scott, Rodney J.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bauer, Denis C.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2015</YEAR><DATE>December</DATE><TITLE>VariantSpark: population scale clustering of genotype information</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>BMC Genomics</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Springer Science + Business Media</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>16</VOLUME><NUMBER>1</NUMBER><ISBN>1471-2164</ISBN><LABEL>OBrien2015</LABEL><URL>10.1186/s12864-015-2269-7</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s12864-015-2269-7</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>34</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Phang, James M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Donald, Steven P.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pandhare, Jui</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Liu, Yongmin</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2008</YEAR><TITLE>The metabolism of proline, a stress substrate, modulates carcinogenic pathways</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Amino Acids</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>35</VOLUME><NUMBER>4</NUMBER><PAGES>681-690</PAGES><ISBN>1438-2199</ISBN><LABEL>Phang.2008</LABEL><ABSTRACT>The resurgence of interest in tumor metabolism has led investigators to emphasize the metabolism of proline as a ``stress substrate'' and to suggest this pathway as a potential anti-tumor target. Proline oxidase, a.k.a. proline dehydrogenase (POX/PRODH), catalyzes the first step in proline degradation and uses proline to generate ATP for survival or reactive oxygen species for programmed cell death. POX/PRODH is induced by p53 under genotoxic stress and initiates apoptosis by both mitochondrial and death receptor pathways. Furthermore, POX/PRODH is induced by PPAR$\gamma$ and its pharmacologic ligands, the thiazolidinediones. The anti-tumor effects of PPAR$\gamma$ may be critically dependent on POX/PRODH. In addition, it is upregulated by nutrient stress through the mTOR pathway to maintain ATP levels. We propose that proline is made available as a stress substrate by the degradation of collagen in the microenvironmental extracellular matrix by matrix metalloproteinases. In a manner analogous to autophagy, this proline-dependent process for bioenergetics from collagen in extracellular matrix can be designated ``ecophagy''.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1007/s00726-008-0063-4</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00726-008-0063-4</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>35</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Rivadeneira, Fernando</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Styrk√°rsdottir, Unnur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Estrada, Karol</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Halld√≥rsson, Bjarni V.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hsu, Yi-Hsiang</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Richards, J. Brent</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zillikens, M. Carola</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kavvoura, Fotini K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Amin, Najaf</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Aulchenko, Yurii S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cupples, L. Adrienne</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Deloukas, Panagiotis</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Demissie, Serkalem</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Grundberg, Elin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hofman, Albert</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kong, Augustine</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Karasik, David</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van Meurs, Joyce B.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Oostra, Ben</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pastinen, Tomi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pols, Huibert A. P.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sigurdsson, Gunnar</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Soranzo, Nicole</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Thorleifsson, Gudmar</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Thorsteinsdottir, Unnur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Williams, Frances M. K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wilson, Scott G.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhou, Yanhua</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ralston, Stuart H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van Duijn, Cornelia M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Spector, Timothy</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kiel, Douglas P.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Stefansson, Kari</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ioannidis, John P. A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Uitterlinden, Andr√© G.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Consortium, the GEnetic Factors For Osteoporosis (GEFOS)</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2009</YEAR><DATE>October</DATE><TITLE>Twenty bone mineral density loci identified by large-scale meta-analysis of genome-wide association studies</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature Genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>41</VOLUME><NUMBER>11</NUMBER><PAGES>1199-1206</PAGES><ISBN>1546-1718</ISBN><LABEL>Rivadeneira2009</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Bone mineral density (BMD) is a heritable complex trait used in the clinical diagnosis of osteoporosis and the assessment of fracture risk. We performed meta-analysis of five genome-wide association studies of femoral neck and lumbar spine BMD in 19,195 subjects of Northern European descent. We identified 20 loci reaching genome-wide significance (GWS; P&#x3c;5√ó10(‚àí8)), of which 13 map to new regions including 1p31.3 (GPR177), 2p21 (SPTBN1), 3p22 (CTNNB1), 4q21.1 (MEPE), 5q14 (MEF2C), 7p14 (STARD3NL), 7q21.3 (FLJ42280), 11p11.2 (LRP4; ARHGAP1; F2), 11p14.1 (DCDC5), 11p15 (SOX6), 16q24 (FOXL1), 17q21 (HDAC5) and 17q12 (CRHR1). The metaanalysis also confirmed at GWS level, seven known BMD loci on 1p36 (ZBTB40), 6q25 (ESR1), 8q24 (TNFRSF11B), 11q13.4 (LRP5), 12q13 (SP7), 13q14 (TNFSF11), and 18q21 (TNFRSF11A). The numerous SNPs associated with BMD map to genes in signaling pathways with relevance to bone metabolism, and highlight the complex genetic architecture underlying osteoporosis and BMD variation.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2783489/</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>16</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>36</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Segal, Mark R.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2004</YEAR><DATE>April</DATE><TITLE>Machine Learning Benchmarks and Random Forest Regression</TITLE><PUBLISHER>Center for Bioinformatics and Molecular Biostatistics</PUBLISHER><LABEL>Segal.2004</LABEL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://escholarship.org/uc/item/35x3v9t4</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>37</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Stagi, Stefano</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lapi, Elisabetta</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gambineri, Eleonora</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Manoni, Cristina</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Genuardi, Maurizio</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Colarusso, Gloria</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Conti, Camilla</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chiarelli, Francesco</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>de Martino, Maurizio</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Azzari, Chiara</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2010</YEAR><DATE>August</DATE><TITLE>Bone density and metabolism in subjects with microdeletion of chromosome 22q11 (del22q11).</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>European Journal of Endocrinology</SECONDARY_TITLE><PLACE_PUBLISHED>England</PLACE_PUBLISHED><VOLUME>163</VOLUME><PAGES>329-37</PAGES><LABEL>Stagi.2010</LABEL><ABSTRACT>INTRODUCTION: Although hypoparathyroidism with hypocalcaemia is one of the most frequent clinical features of monoallelic microdeletion of chromosome 22q11 (22q11DS), bone mass and metabolism have not yet been assessed in these patients. DESIGN: This study aimed to evaluate bone mass and metabolism in a cohort of patients, both children and adults, with 22q11DS. METHODS: In twenty-eight patients with 22q11DS (median age 12.5, range 6.1-42.8 years), serum levels of ionised and total calcium, phosphate, parathyroid hormone (PTH), 25-hydroxyvitamin D, 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D, osteocalcin and bone-specific alkaline phosphatase (BSAP), and urinary deoxypyridinoline concentrations were evaluated. In these patients, bone mineral density (BMD) was evaluated by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) examination, and volumetric BMD (bone mineral apparent density (BMAD)) was calculated. The data obtained from paediatric and adult patients were compared with two age-, sex- and body size-matched healthy subject control groups. RESULTS: Patients with 22q11DS showed a reduced BMAD Z-score compared with controls (P&#x3c;0.001). These patients also had significantly lower ionised (P&#x3c;0.001) and total calcium (P&#x3c;0.05) levels as well as lower PTH levels (P&#x3c;0.05), compared with the controls. In particular, children and young patients with 22q11DS had significantly lower serum osteocalcin levels (P&#x3c;0.001), BSAP levels (P&#x3c;0.001) and urinary deoxypyridinoline concentrations (P&#x3c;0.001) than controls. These results were not confirmed in adults. Finally, patients with hypoparathyroidism and/or hypocalcaemia at the time of the study showed significantly lower ionised (P&#x3c;0.001) and total calcium levels (P&#x3c;0.001), PTH levels (P&#x3c;0.05), BSAP levels (P&#x3c;0.001), osteocalcin levels (P&#x3c;0.001) and urinary deoxypyridinoline concentrations (P&#x3c;0.001), compared with patients without hypoparathyroidism and/or hypocalcaemia. Nonetheless, the BMAD Z-score did not show substantial differences between these two groups. CONCLUSIONS: Subjects with 22q11DS have a significant reduction in bone mass that appears to be more severe in adults who have already attained peak bone mass than in children who are still growing. Therefore, we suggest a close monitoring of bone mass and metabolism in 22q11DS patients.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Eur J Endocrinol. 2010 Aug;163(2):329-37. doi: 10.1530/EJE-10-0167. Epub 2010 Jun 1.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>38</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Strobl, Carolin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Boulesteix, Anne-Laure</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zeileis, Achim</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hothorn, Torsten</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2007</YEAR><TITLE>Bias in Random Forest Variable Importance Measures: Illustrations, Sources and a Solution</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>BMC Bioinformatics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>8</VOLUME><PAGES>25</PAGES><LABEL>Strobl.et.al.2007</LABEL><NOTES>highly accessed</NOTES><URL>10.1186/1471-2105-8-25</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2105/8/25/abstract</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>39</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Szymczak, Silke</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Holzinger, Emily</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dasgupta, Abhijit</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Malley, James D.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Molloy, Anne M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mills, James L.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Brody, Lawrence C.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Stambolian, Dwight</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bailey-Wilson, Joan E.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2016</YEAR><TITLE>r2VIM: A new variable selection method for random forests in genome-wide association studies.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>BioData Mining</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Statistical Genetics Section, Inherited Disease Research Branch, National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, 333 Cassell Dr, 21224 Baltimore, USA.</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>9</VOLUME><PAGES>7</PAGES><LABEL>Szymczak2016</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Machine learning methods and in particular random forests (RFs) are a promising alternative to standard single SNP analyses in genome-wide association studies (GWAS). RFs provide variable importance measures (VIMs) to rank SNPs according to their predictive power. However, in contrast to the established genome-wide significance threshold, no clear criteria exist to determine how many SNPs should be selected for downstream analyses.We propose a new variable selection approach, recurrent relative variable importance measure (r2VIM). Importance values are calculated relative to an observed minimal importance score for several runs of RF and only SNPs with large relative VIMs in all of the runs are selected as important. Evaluations on simulated GWAS data show that the new method controls the number of false-positives under the null hypothesis. Under a simple alternative hypothesis with several independent main effects it is only slightly less powerful than logistic regression. In an experimental GWAS data set, the same strong signal is identified while the approach selects none of the SNPs in an underpowered GWAS.The novel variable selection method r2VIM is a promising extension to standard RF for objectively selecting relevant SNPs in GWAS while controlling the number of false-positive results.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1186/s13040-016-0087-3</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s13040-016-0087-3</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>1</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>40</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Thakker, Rajesh V</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Whyte, Michael P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eisman, John</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Igarashi, Takashi</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2012</YEAR><TITLE>Genetics of bone biology and skeletal disease</TITLE><PUBLISHER>Academic Press</PUBLISHER><LABEL>Thakker2012</LABEL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>41</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Tuv, Eugene</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Borisov, Alexander</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Runger, George</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Torkkola, Kari</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2009</YEAR><DATE>December</DATE><TITLE>Feature Selection with Ensembles, Artificial Variables, and Redundancy Elimination</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Journal of Machine Learning Research</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>JMLR.org</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>10</VOLUME><PAGES>1341-1366</PAGES><ISBN>1532-4435</ISBN><LABEL>Tuv.et.al.2009</LABEL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1577069.1755828</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>42</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Webber, William</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Moffat, Alistair</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zobel, Justin</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2010</YEAR><DATE>November</DATE><TITLE>A Similarity Measure for Indefinite Rankings</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>ACM Transactions on Information Systems</SECONDARY_TITLE><PLACE_PUBLISHED>New York, NY, USA</PLACE_PUBLISHED><PUBLISHER>ACM</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>28</VOLUME><NUMBER>4</NUMBER><PAGES>20:1-20:38</PAGES><ISBN>1046-8188</ISBN><LABEL>Webber2010</LABEL><URL>10.1145/1852102.1852106</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1852102.1852106</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>43</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Welter, Danielle</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>MacArthur, Jacqueline</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Morales, Joannella</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Burdett, Tony</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hall, Peggy</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Junkins, Heather</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Klemm, Alan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Flicek, Paul</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Manolio, Teri</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hindorff, Lucia</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>al. , et</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2013</YEAR><DATE>Dec</DATE><TITLE>The NHGRI GWAS Catalog, a curated resource of SNP-trait associations</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nucleic Acids Research</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Oxford University Press (OUP)</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>42</VOLUME><NUMBER>D1</NUMBER><PAGES>D1001-D1006</PAGES><ISBN>1362-4962</ISBN><LABEL>Welter2013</LABEL><URL>10.1093/nar/gkt1229</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkt1229</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>44</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Wright, M. N.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ziegler, A.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2016</YEAR><TITLE>Ranger: A Fast Implementation of Random Forests for High Dimensional Data in C++ and R</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Journal of Statistical Software</SECONDARY_TITLE><LABEL>Wright.and.Ziegle.2016</LABEL><NOTES>in press</NOTES><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://arxiv.org/abs/1508.04409</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>45</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Wright, Marvin N.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ziegler, Andreas</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>K&#x00F6;nig, Inke R.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2016</YEAR><TITLE>Do little interactions get lost in dark random forests?</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>BMC Bioinformatics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>17</VOLUME><NUMBER>1</NUMBER><PAGES>145</PAGES><ISBN>1471-2105</ISBN><LABEL>Wright.et.al.2016</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Random forests have often been claimed to uncover interaction effects. However, if and how interaction effects can be differentiated from marginal effects remains unclear. In extensive simulation studies, we investigate whether random forest variable importance measures capture or detect gene-gene interactions. With capturing interactions, we define the ability to identify a variable that acts through an interaction with another one, while detection is the ability to identify an interaction effect as such.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1186/s12859-016-0995-8</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s12859-016-0995-8</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>46</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yang, Jian</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Manolio, Teri A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pasquale, Louis R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Boerwinkle, Eric</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Caporaso, Neil</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cunningham, Julie M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>de Andrade, Mariza</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Feenstra, Bjarke</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Feingold, Eleanor</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hayes, M Geoffrey</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hill, William G.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Landi, Maria Teresa</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Alonso, Alvaro</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lettre, Guillaume</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lin, Peng</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ling, Hua</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lowe, William</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mathias, Rasika A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Melbye, Mads</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pugh, Elizabeth</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cornelis, Marilyn C.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Weir, Bruce S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Goddard, Michael E.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Visscher, Peter M.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2011</YEAR><DATE>June</DATE><TITLE>Genome partitioning of genetic variation for complex traits using common SNPs.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature Genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Queensland Statistical Genetics Laboratory, Queensland Institute of Medical Research, Brisbane, Australia.</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>43</VOLUME><NUMBER>6</NUMBER><PAGES>519-525</PAGES><LABEL>Yang2011</LABEL><URL>10.1038/ng.823</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.823</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>47</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yano, Kenji</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, Eiji</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Aya, Koichiro</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takeuchi, Hideyuki</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lo, Pei-Ching</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hu, Li</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamasaki, Masanori</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yoshida, Shinya</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kitano, Hidemi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hirano, Ko</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Matsuoka, Makoto</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2016</YEAR><DATE>August</DATE><TITLE>Genome-wide association study using whole-genome sequencing rapidly identifies new genes influencing agronomic traits in rice.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature Genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><PUBLISHER>Bioscience and Biotechnology Center, Nagoya University, Nagoya, Japan.</PUBLISHER><VOLUME>48</VOLUME><NUMBER>8</NUMBER><PAGES>927-934</PAGES><LABEL>Yano2016</LABEL><ABSTRACT>A genome-wide association study (GWAS) can be a powerful tool for the identification of genes associated with agronomic traits in crop species, but it is often hindered by population structure and the large extent of linkage disequilibrium. In this study, we identified agronomically important genes in rice using GWAS based on whole-genome sequencing, followed by the screening of candidate genes based on the estimated effect of nucleotide polymorphisms. Using this approach, we identified four new genes associated with agronomic traits. Some genes were undetectable by standard SNP analysis, but we detected them using gene-based association analysis. This study provides fundamental insights relevant to the rapid identification of genes associated with agronomic traits using GWAS and will accelerate future efforts aimed at crop improvement.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1038/ng.3596</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.3596</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>16</REFERENCE_TYPE><TITLE>DECODE: Decipherment of DNA Elements</TITLE><LABEL>DECODE</LABEL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>http://www.sabiosciences.com/chipqpcrsearch.php?app=TFBS</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>48</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Nielson, Carrie M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Liu, Ching-Ti</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Smith, Albert V</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ackert-Bicknell, Cheryl L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Reppe, Sjur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jakobsdottir, Johanna</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wassel, Christina</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Register, Thomas C</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Oei, Ling</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Alonso, Nerea</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Oei, Edwin H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Parimi, Neeta</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Samelson, Elizabeth J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nalls, Mike A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zmuda, Joseph</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lang, Thomas</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bouxsein, Mary</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Latourelle, Jeanne</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Claussnitzer, Melina</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Siggeirsdottir, Kristin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Srikanth, Priya</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lorentzen, Erik</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Vandenput, Liesbeth</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Langefeld, Carl</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Raffield, Laura</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Terry, Greg</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cox, Amanda J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Allison, Matthew A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Criqui, Michael H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bowden, Don</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ikram, M Arfan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mellström, Dan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Karlsson, Magnus K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Carr, John</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Budoff, Matthew</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Phillips, Caroline</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cupples, L Adrienne</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chou, Wen-Chi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Myers, Richard H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ralston, Stuart H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gautvik, Kaare M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cawthon, Peggy M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cummings, Steven</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Karasik, David</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rivadeneira, Fernando</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gudnason, Vilmundur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Orwoll, Eric S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Harris, Tamara B</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohlsson, Claes</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kiel, Douglas P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hsu, Yi-Hsiang</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2016</YEAR><DATE>December</DATE><TITLE>Novel Genetic Variants Associated With Increased Vertebral Volumetric BMD, Reduced Vertebral Fracture Risk, and Increased Expression of SLC1A3 and EPHB2.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Journal of bone and mineral research : the official journal of the American Society for Bone and Mineral Research</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>31</VOLUME><PAGES>2085-2097</PAGES><ISBN>1523-4681</ISBN><LABEL>Nielson2016</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Genome-wide association studies (GWASs) have revealed numerous loci for areal bone mineral density (aBMD). We completed the first GWAS meta-analysis (n = 15,275) of lumbar spine volumetric BMD (vBMD) measured by quantitative computed tomography (QCT), allowing for examination of the trabecular bone compartment. SNPs that were significantly associated with vBMD were also examined in two GWAS meta-analyses to determine associations with morphometric vertebral fracture (n = 21,701) and clinical vertebral fracture (n = 5893). Expression quantitative trait locus (eQTL) analyses of iliac crest biopsies were performed in 84 postmenopausal women, and murine osteoblast expression of genes implicated by eQTL or by proximity to vBMD-associated SNPs was examined. We identified significant vBMD associations with five loci, including: 1p36.12, containing WNT4 and ZBTB40; 8q24, containing TNFRSF11B; and 13q14, containing AKAP11 and TNFSF11. Two loci (5p13 and 1p36.12) also contained associations with radiographic and clinical vertebral fracture, respectively. In 5p13, rs2468531 (minor allele frequency [MAF] = 3%) was associated with higher vBMD (β = 0.22, p = 1.9 × 10(-8) ) and decreased risk of radiographic vertebral fracture (odds ratio [OR] = 0.75; false discovery rate [FDR] p = 0.01). In 1p36.12, rs12742784 (MAF = 21%) was associated with higher vBMD (β = 0.09, p = 1.2 × 10(-10) ) and decreased risk of clinical vertebral fracture (OR = 0.82; FDR p = 7.4 × 10(-4) ). Both SNPs are noncoding and were associated with increased mRNA expression levels in human bone biopsies: rs2468531 with SLC1A3 (β = 0.28, FDR p = 0.01, involved in glutamate signaling and osteogenic response to mechanical loading) and rs12742784 with EPHB2 (β = 0.12, FDR p = 1.7 × 10(-3) , functions in bone-related ephrin signaling). Both genes are expressed in murine osteoblasts. This is the first study to link SLC1A3 and EPHB2 to clinically relevant vertebral osteoporosis phenotypes. These results may help elucidate vertebral bone biology and novel approaches to reducing vertebral fracture incidence. © 2016 American Society for Bone and Mineral Research.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1002/jbmr.2913</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>49</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Estrada, Karol</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Styrkarsdottir, Unnur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Evangelou, Evangelos</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hsu, Yi-Hsiang</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Duncan, Emma L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ntzani, Evangelia E</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Oei, Ling</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Albagha, Omar M E</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Amin, Najaf</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kemp, John P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Koller, Daniel L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Li, Guo</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Liu, Ching-Ti</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Minster, Ryan L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Moayyeri, Alireza</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Vandenput, Liesbeth</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Willner, Dana</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Xiao, Su-Mei</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yerges-Armstrong, Laura M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zheng, Hou-Feng</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Alonso, Nerea</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eriksson, Joel</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kammerer, Candace M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kaptoge, Stephen K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Leo, Paul J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Thorleifsson, Gudmar</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wilson, Scott G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wilson, James F</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Aalto, Ville</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Alen, Markku</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Aragaki, Aaron K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Aspelund, Thor</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Center, Jacqueline R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dailiana, Zoe</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Duggan, David J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Garcia, Melissa</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Garcia-Giralt, Natàlia</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Giroux, Sylvie</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hallmans, Göran</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hocking, Lynne J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Husted, Lise Bjerre</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jameson, Karen A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Khusainova, Rita</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kim, Ghi Su</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kooperberg, Charles</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Koromila, Theodora</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kruk, Marcin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Laaksonen, Marika</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lacroix, Andrea Z</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lee, Seung Hun</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Leung, Ping C</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lewis, Joshua R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Masi, Laura</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mencej-Bedrac, Simona</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nguyen, Tuan V</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nogues, Xavier</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Patel, Millan S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Prezelj, Janez</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rose, Lynda M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Scollen, Serena</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Siggeirsdottir, Kristin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Smith, Albert V</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Svensson, Olle</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Trompet, Stella</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Trummer, Olivia</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van Schoor, Natasja M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Woo, Jean</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhu, Kun</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Balcells, Susana</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Brandi, Maria Luisa</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Buckley, Brendan M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cheng, Sulin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Christiansen, Claus</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cooper, Cyrus</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dedoussis, George</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ford, Ian</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Frost, Morten</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Goltzman, David</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>González-Macías, Jesús</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kähönen, Mika</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Karlsson, Magnus</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Khusnutdinova, Elza</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Koh, Jung-Min</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kollia, Panagoula</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Langdahl, Bente Lomholt</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Leslie, William D</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lips, Paul</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ljunggren, Östen</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lorenc, Roman S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Marc, Janja</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mellström, Dan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Obermayer-Pietsch, Barbara</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Olmos, José M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pettersson-Kymmer, Ulrika</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Reid, David M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Riancho, José A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ridker, Paul M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rousseau, François</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Slagboom, P Eline</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tang, Nelson L S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Urreizti, Roser</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Van Hul, Wim</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Viikari, Jorma</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zarrabeitia, María T</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Aulchenko, Yurii S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Castano-Betancourt, Martha</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Grundberg, Elin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Herrera, Lizbeth</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ingvarsson, Thorvaldur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Johannsdottir, Hrefna</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kwan, Tony</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Li, Rui</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Luben, Robert</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Medina-Gómez, Carolina</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Palsson, Stefan Th</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Reppe, Sjur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rotter, Jerome I</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sigurdsson, Gunnar</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van Meurs, Joyce B J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Verlaan, Dominique</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Williams, Frances M K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wood, Andrew R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhou, Yanhua</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gautvik, Kaare M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pastinen, Tomi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Raychaudhuri, Soumya</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cauley, Jane A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chasman, Daniel I</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Clark, Graeme R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cummings, Steven R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Danoy, Patrick</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dennison, Elaine M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eastell, Richard</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eisman, John A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gudnason, Vilmundur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hofman, Albert</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jackson, Rebecca D</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jones, Graeme</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jukema, J Wouter</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Khaw, Kay-Tee</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lehtimäki, Terho</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Liu, Yongmei</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lorentzon, Mattias</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>McCloskey, Eugene</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mitchell, Braxton D</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nandakumar, Kannabiran</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nicholson, Geoffrey C</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Oostra, Ben A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Peacock, Munro</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pols, Huibert A P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Prince, Richard L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Raitakari, Olli</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Reid, Ian R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Robbins, John</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sambrook, Philip N</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sham, Pak Chung</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Shuldiner, Alan R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tylavsky, Frances A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van Duijn, Cornelia M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wareham, Nick J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cupples, L Adrienne</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Econs, Michael J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Evans, David M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Harris, Tamara B</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kung, Annie Wai Chee</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Psaty, Bruce M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Reeve, Jonathan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Spector, Timothy D</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Streeten, Elizabeth A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zillikens, M Carola</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Thorsteinsdottir, Unnur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohlsson, Claes</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Karasik, David</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Richards, J Brent</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Brown, Matthew A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Stefansson, Kari</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Uitterlinden, André G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ralston, Stuart H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ioannidis, John P A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kiel, Douglas P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rivadeneira, Fernando</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2012</YEAR><DATE>April</DATE><TITLE>Genome-wide meta-analysis identifies 56 bone mineral density loci and reveals 14 loci associated with risk of fracture.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>44</VOLUME><PAGES>491-501</PAGES><ISBN>1546-1718</ISBN><LABEL>Estrada2012</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Bone mineral density (BMD) is the most widely used predictor of fracture risk. We performed the largest meta-analysis to date on lumbar spine and femoral neck BMD, including 17 genome-wide association studies and 32,961 individuals of European and east Asian ancestry. We tested the top BMD-associated markers for replication in 50,933 independent subjects and for association with risk of low-trauma fracture in 31,016 individuals with a history of fracture (cases) and 102,444 controls. We identified 56 loci (32 new) associated with BMD at genome-wide significance (P &#x3c; 5 × 10(-8)). Several of these factors cluster within the RANK-RANKL-OPG, mesenchymal stem cell differentiation, endochondral ossification and Wnt signaling pathways. However, we also discovered loci that were localized to genes not known to have a role in bone biology. Fourteen BMD-associated loci were also associated with fracture risk (P &#x3c; 5 × 10(-4), Bonferroni corrected), of which six reached P &#x3c; 5 × 10(-8), including at 18p11.21 (FAM210A), 7q21.3 (SLC25A13), 11q13.2 (LRP5), 4q22.1 (MEPE), 2p16.2 (SPTBN1) and 10q21.1 (DKK1). These findings shed light on the genetic architecture and pathophysiological mechanisms underlying BMD variation and fracture susceptibility.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1038/ng.2249</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>50</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Dengler-Crish, Christine M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Smith, Matthew A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wilson, Gina N</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2017</YEAR><TITLE>Early Evidence of Low Bone Density and Decreased Serotonergic Synthesis in the Dorsal Raphe of a Tauopathy Model of Alzheimer's Disease.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Journal of Alzheimer's disease : JAD</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>55</VOLUME><PAGES>1605-1619</PAGES><ISBN>1875-8908</ISBN><LABEL>Dengler-Crish2017</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Reduced bone mineral density (BMD) and its clinical sequelae, osteoporosis, occur at a much greater rate in patients with Alzheimer's disease (AD), often emerging early in the disease before significant cognitive decline is seen. Reduced BMD translates to increased bone fracture risk, decreased quality of life, and increased mortality for AD patients. However, the mechanism responsible for this observation is unclear. We hypothesize that bone loss is an additional component of an AD prodrome-changes that emerge prior to dementia and are mediated by dysfunction of the central serotonergic pathways. We characterized the skeletal phenotype of htau mice that express human forms of the microtubule-associated protein tau that become pathologically hyperphosphorylated in AD. Using radiographic densitometry, we measured BMD in female and male htau mice from 2-6 months of age-time-points prior to the presence of significant tauopathy in the hippocampal/entorhinal regions characteristic of this model. We found a significantly reduced BMD phenotype in htau mice that was most pronounced in males. Using western blotting and immunofluorescence, we showed overall reduced tryptophan hydroxylase (TPH) protein in htau brainstem and a 70% reduction in TPH-positive cells in the dorsal raphe nucleus (DRN)-a pivotal structure in the regulation of the adult skeleton. Elevations of hyperphosphorylated tau (ptau) proteins were also measured in brainstem, and co-labeled immunofluorescence studies showed presence of ptau in TPH-positive cells of the DRN as early as 4 months of age in htau mice. Together, these findings demonstrate that reduced BMD occurs earlier than overt degeneration in a tau-based AD model and that pathological changes in tau phosphorylation occur in the serotonin-producing neurons of the brainstem raphe in these mice. This illuminates a need to define a mechanistic relationship between bone loss and serotonergic deficits in early AD.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.3233/JAD-160658</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>51</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Woolfe, Adam</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Goodson, Martin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Goode, Debbie K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Snell, Phil</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>McEwen, Gayle K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Vavouri, Tanya</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Smith, Sarah F</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>North, Phil</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Callaway, Heather</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kelly, Krys</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Walter, Klaudia</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Abnizova, Irina</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gilks, Walter</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Edwards, Yvonne J K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cooke, Julie E</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Elgar, Greg</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2005</YEAR><DATE>January</DATE><TITLE>Highly conserved non-coding sequences are associated with vertebrate development.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>PLoS biology</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>3</VOLUME><PAGES>e7</PAGES><ISBN>1545-7885</ISBN><LABEL>Woolfe2005</LABEL><ABSTRACT>In addition to protein coding sequence, the human genome contains a significant amount of regulatory DNA, the identification of which is proving somewhat recalcitrant to both in silico and functional methods. An approach that has been used with some success is comparative sequence analysis, whereby equivalent genomic regions from different organisms are compared in order to identify both similarities and differences. In general, similarities in sequence between highly divergent organisms imply functional constraint. We have used a whole-genome comparison between humans and the pufferfish, Fugu rubripes, to identify nearly 1,400 highly conserved non-coding sequences. Given the evolutionary divergence between these species, it is likely that these sequences are found in, and furthermore are essential to, all vertebrates. Most, and possibly all, of these sequences are located in and around genes that act as developmental regulators. Some of these sequences are over 90% identical across more than 500 bases, being more highly conserved than coding sequence between these two species. Despite this, we cannot find any similar sequences in invertebrate genomes. In order to begin to functionally test this set of sequences, we have used a rapid in vivo assay system using zebrafish embryos that allows tissue-specific enhancer activity to be identified. Functional data is presented for highly conserved non-coding sequences associated with four unrelated developmental regulators (SOX21, PAX6, HLXB9, and SHH), in order to demonstrate the suitability of this screen to a wide range of genes and expression patterns. Of 25 sequence elements tested around these four genes, 23 show significant enhancer activity in one or more tissues. We have identified a set of non-coding sequences that are highly conserved throughout vertebrates. They are found in clusters across the human genome, principally around genes that are implicated in the regulation of development, including many transcription factors. These highly conserved non-coding sequences are likely to form part of the genomic circuitry that uniquely defines vertebrate development.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1371/journal.pbio.0030007</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>52</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Pei, Y-F</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Xie, Z-G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wang, X-Y</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hu, W-Z</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Li, L-B</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ran, S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lin, Y</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hai, R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Shen, H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tian, Q</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhang, Y-H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lei, S-F</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Papasian, C J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Deng, H-W</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhang, L</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2016</YEAR><DATE>November</DATE><TITLE>Association of 3q13.32 variants with hip trochanter and intertrochanter bone mineral density identified by a genome-wide association study.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Osteoporosis international : a journal established as result of cooperation between the European Foundation for Osteoporosis and the National Osteoporosis Foundation of the USA</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>27</VOLUME><PAGES>3343-3354</PAGES><ISBN>1433-2965</ISBN><LABEL>Pei2016</LABEL><ABSTRACT>We performed a GWAS of trochanter and intertrochanter bone mineral density (BMD) in the Framingham Heart Study and replicated in three independent studies. Our results identified one novel locus around the associated variations at chromosomal region 3q13.32 and replicated two loci at chromosomal regions 3p21 and 8q24. Our findings provide useful insights that enhance our understanding of bone development, osteoporosis, and fracture pathogenesis. Hip trochanter (TRO) and intertrochanter (INT) subregions have important clinical relevance to subtrochanteric and intertrochanteric fractures but have rarely been studied by genome-wide association studies (GWASs). Aiming to identify genomic loci associated with BMD variation at TRO and INT regions, we performed a GWAS utilizing the Framingham Heart Study (FHS, N = 6,912) as discovery sample and utilized the Women's Health Initiative (WHI) African-American subsample (N = 845), WHI Hispanic subsample (N = 446), and Omaha osteoporosis study (N = 971), for replication. Combining the evidence from both the discovery and the replication samples, we identified one novel locus around the associated variations at chromosomal region 3q13.32 (rs1949542, discovery p = 6.16 × 10(-8), replication p = 2.86 × 10(-4) for INT-BMD; discovery p = 1.35 × 10(-7), replication p = 4.16 × 10(-4) for TRO-BMD, closest gene RP11-384F7.1). We also replicated two loci at chromosomal regions 3p21 (rs148725943, discovery p = 6.61 × 10(-7), replication p = 5.22 × 10(-4) for TRO-BMD, closest gene CTNNB1) and 8q24 (rs7839059, discovery p = 2.28 × 10(-7), replication p = 1.55 × 10(-3) for TRO-BMD, closest gene TNFRSF11B) that were reported previously. We demonstrated that the effects at both 3q13.32 and 3p21 were specific to the TRO, but not to the femoral neck and spine. In contrast, the effect at 8q24 was common to all the sites. Our findings provide useful insights that enhance our understanding of bone development, osteoporosis, and fracture pathogenesis.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1007/s00198-016-3663-y</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>53</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Rivadeneira, Fernando</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Styrkársdottir, Unnur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Estrada, Karol</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Halldórsson, Bjarni V</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hsu, Yi-Hsiang</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Richards, J Brent</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zillikens, M Carola</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kavvoura, Fotini K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Amin, Najaf</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Aulchenko, Yurii S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cupples, L Adrienne</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Deloukas, Panagiotis</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Demissie, Serkalem</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Grundberg, Elin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hofman, Albert</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kong, Augustine</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Karasik, David</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van Meurs, Joyce B</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Oostra, Ben</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pastinen, Tomi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pols, Huibert A P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sigurdsson, Gunnar</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Soranzo, Nicole</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Thorleifsson, Gudmar</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Thorsteinsdottir, Unnur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Williams, Frances M K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wilson, Scott G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhou, Yanhua</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ralston, Stuart H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van Duijn, Cornelia M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Spector, Timothy</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kiel, Douglas P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Stefansson, Kari</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ioannidis, John P A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Uitterlinden, André G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>for Osteoporosis (GEFOS) Consortium, Genetic Factors</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2009</YEAR><DATE>November</DATE><TITLE>Twenty bone-mineral-density loci identified by large-scale meta-analysis of genome-wide association studies.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>41</VOLUME><PAGES>1199-1206</PAGES><ISBN>1546-1718</ISBN><LABEL>Rivadeneira2009a</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Bone mineral density (BMD) is a heritable complex trait used in the clinical diagnosis of osteoporosis and the assessment of fracture risk. We performed meta-analysis of five genome-wide association studies of femoral neck and lumbar spine BMD in 19,195 subjects of Northern European descent. We identified 20 BMD loci that reached genome-wide significance (GWS; P &#x3c; 5 x 10(-8)), of which 13 map to regions not previously associated with this trait: 1p31.3 (GPR177), 2p21 (SPTBN1), 3p22 (CTNNB1), 4q21.1 (MEPE), 5q14 (MEF2C), 7p14 (STARD3NL), 7q21.3 (FLJ42280), 11p11.2 (LRP4, ARHGAP1, F2), 11p14.1 (DCDC5), 11p15 (SOX6), 16q24 (FOXL1), 17q21 (HDAC5) and 17q12 (CRHR1). The meta-analysis also confirmed at GWS level seven known BMD loci on 1p36 (ZBTB40), 6q25 (ESR1), 8q24 (TNFRSF11B), 11q13.4 (LRP5), 12q13 (SP7), 13q14 (TNFSF11) and 18q21 (TNFRSF11A). The many SNPs associated with BMD map to genes in signaling pathways with relevance to bone metabolism and highlight the complex genetic architecture that underlies osteoporosis and variation in BMD.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1038/ng.446</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>54</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Pei, Yu-Fang</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hu, Wen-Zhu</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hai, Rong</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wang, Xiu-Yan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ran, Shu</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lin, Yong</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Shen, Hui</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tian, Qing</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Consortium, GEFOS-seq</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Consortium, AOGC</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Consortium, UK10K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lei, Shu-Feng</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhang, Yong-Hong</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Papasian, Christopher J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Deng, Hong-Wen</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhang, Lei</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2016</YEAR><DATE>October</DATE><TITLE>Genome-wide association meta-analyses identified 1q43 and 2q32.2 for hip Ward's triangle areal bone mineral density.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Bone</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>91</VOLUME><PAGES>1-10</PAGES><ISBN>1873-2763</ISBN><LABEL>Pei2016a</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Aiming to identify genomic variants associated with osteoporosis, we performed a genome-wide association meta-analysis of bone mineral density (BMD) at Ward's triangle of the hip in 7175 subjects from 6 samples. We performed in silico replications with femoral neck, trochanter, and inter-trochanter BMDs in 6912 subjects from the Framingham heart study (FHS), and with forearm, femoral neck and lumbar spine BMDs in 32965 subjects from the GEFOS summary results. Combining the evidence from all samples, we identified 2 novel loci for areal BMD: 1q43 (rs1414660, discovery p=1.20×10(-8), FHS p=0.05 for trochanter BMD; rs9287237, discovery p=3.55×10(-7), FHS p=9.20×10(-3) for trochanter BMD, GEFOS p=0.02 for forearm BMD, nearest gene FMN2) and 2q32.2 (rs56346965, discovery p=7.48×10(-7), FHS p=0.10 for inter-trochanter BMD, GEFOS p=0.02 for spine BMD, nearest gene NAB1). The two lead SNPs rs1414660 and rs56346965 are eQTL sites for the genes GREM2 and NAB1 respectively. Functional annotation of GREM2 and NAB1 illustrated their involvement in BMP signaling pathway and in bone development. We also replicated three previously reported loci: 5q14.3 (rs10037512, discovery p=3.09×10(-6), FHS p=8.50×10(-3), GEFOS p=1.23×10(-24) for femoral neck BMD, nearest gene MEF2C), 6q25.1 (rs3020340, discovery p=1.64×10(-6), GEFOS p=1.69×10(-3) for SPN-BMD, nearest gene ESR1) and 7q21.3 (rs13310130, discovery p=8.79×10(-7), GEFOS p=2.61×10(-7) for spine BMD, nearest gene SHFM1). Our findings provide additional insights that further enhance our understanding of bone development, osteoporosis, and fracture pathogenesis.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1016/j.bone.2016.07.004</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>55</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Zhang, Lei</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Choi, Hyung Jin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Estrada, Karol</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Leo, Paul J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Li, Jian</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pei, Yu-Fang</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhang, Yinping</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lin, Yong</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Shen, Hui</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Liu, Yao-Zhong</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Liu, Yongjun</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhao, Yingchun</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhang, Ji-Gang</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tian, Qing</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wang, Yu-ping</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Han, Yingying</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ran, Shu</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hai, Rong</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhu, Xue-Zhen</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wu, Shuyan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yan, Han</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Liu, Xiaogang</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yang, Tie-Lin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Guo, Yan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhang, Feng</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Guo, Yan-fang</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chen, Yuan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chen, Xiangding</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tan, Lijun</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhang, Lishu</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Deng, Fei-Yan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Deng, Hongyi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rivadeneira, Fernando</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Duncan, Emma L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lee, Jong Young</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Han, Bok Ghee</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cho, Nam H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nicholson, Geoffrey C</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>McCloskey, Eugene</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eastell, Richard</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Prince, Richard L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eisman, John A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jones, Graeme</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Reid, Ian R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sambrook, Philip N</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dennison, Elaine M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Danoy, Patrick</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yerges-Armstrong, Laura M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Streeten, Elizabeth A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hu, Tian</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Xiang, Shuanglin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Papasian, Christopher J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Brown, Matthew A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Shin, Chan Soo</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Uitterlinden, André G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Deng, Hong-Wen</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2014</YEAR><DATE>April</DATE><TITLE>Multistage genome-wide association meta-analyses identified two new loci for bone mineral density.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Human molecular genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>23</VOLUME><PAGES>1923-1933</PAGES><ISBN>1460-2083</ISBN><LABEL>Zhang2014</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Aiming to identify novel genetic variants and to confirm previously identified genetic variants associated with bone mineral density (BMD), we conducted a three-stage genome-wide association (GWA) meta-analysis in 27 061 study subjects. Stage 1 meta-analyzed seven GWA samples and 11 140 subjects for BMDs at the lumbar spine, hip and femoral neck, followed by a Stage 2 in silico replication of 33 SNPs in 9258 subjects, and by a Stage 3 de novo validation of three SNPs in 6663 subjects. Combining evidence from all the stages, we have identified two novel loci that have not been reported previously at the genome-wide significance (GWS; 5.0 × 10(-8)) level: 14q24.2 (rs227425, P-value 3.98 × 10(-13), SMOC1) in the combined sample of males and females and 21q22.13 (rs170183, P-value 4.15 × 10(-9), CLDN14) in the female-specific sample. The two newly identified SNPs were also significant in the GEnetic Factors for OSteoporosis consortium (GEFOS, n = 32 960) summary results. We have also independently confirmed 13 previously reported loci at the GWS level: 1p36.12 (ZBTB40), 1p31.3 (GPR177), 4p16.3 (FGFRL1), 4q22.1 (MEPE), 5q14.3 (MEF2C), 6q25.1 (C6orf97, ESR1), 7q21.3 (FLJ42280, SHFM1), 7q31.31 (FAM3C, WNT16), 8q24.12 (TNFRSF11B), 11p15.3 (SOX6), 11q13.4 (LRP5), 13q14.11 (AKAP11) and 16q24 (FOXL1). Gene expression analysis in osteogenic cells implied potential functional association of the two candidate genes (SMOC1 and CLDN14) in bone metabolism. Our findings independently confirm previously identified biological pathways underlying bone metabolism and contribute to the discovery of novel pathways, thus providing valuable insights into the intervention and treatment of osteoporosis.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1093/hmg/ddt575</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>56</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Kemp, John P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Medina-Gomez, Carolina</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Estrada, Karol</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>St Pourcain, Beate</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Heppe, Denise H M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Warrington, Nicole M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Oei, Ling</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ring, Susan M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kruithof, Claudia J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Timpson, Nicholas J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wolber, Lisa E</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Reppe, Sjur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gautvik, Kaare</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Grundberg, Elin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ge, Bing</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van der Eerden, Bram</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van de Peppel, Jeroen</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hibbs, Matthew A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ackert-Bicknell, Cheryl L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Choi, Kwangbom</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Koller, Daniel L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Econs, Michael J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Williams, Frances M K</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Foroud, Tatiana</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zillikens, M Carola</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohlsson, Claes</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hofman, Albert</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Uitterlinden, André G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Davey Smith, George</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jaddoe, Vincent W V</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tobias, Jonathan H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rivadeneira, Fernando</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Evans, David M</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2014</YEAR><DATE>June</DATE><TITLE>Phenotypic dissection of bone mineral density reveals skeletal site specificity and facilitates the identification of novel loci in the genetic regulation of bone mass attainment.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>PLoS genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>10</VOLUME><PAGES>e1004423</PAGES><ISBN>1553-7404</ISBN><LABEL>Kemp2014a</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Heritability of bone mineral density (BMD) varies across skeletal sites, reflecting different relative contributions of genetic and environmental influences. To quantify the degree to which common genetic variants tag and environmental factors influence BMD, at different sites, we estimated the genetic (rg) and residual (re) correlations between BMD measured at the upper limbs (UL-BMD), lower limbs (LL-BMD) and skull (SK-BMD), using total-body DXA scans of ∼ 4,890 participants recruited by the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and their Children (ALSPAC). Point estimates of rg indicated that appendicular sites have a greater proportion of shared genetic architecture (LL-/UL-BMD rg = 0.78) between them, than with the skull (UL-/SK-BMD rg = 0.58 and LL-/SK-BMD rg = 0.43). Likewise, the residual correlation between BMD at appendicular sites (r(e) = 0.55) was higher than the residual correlation between SK-BMD and BMD at appendicular sites (r(e) = 0.20-0.24). To explore the basis for the observed differences in rg and re, genome-wide association meta-analyses were performed (n ∼ 9,395), combining data from ALSPAC and the Generation R Study identifying 15 independent signals from 13 loci associated at genome-wide significant level across different skeletal regions. Results suggested that previously identified BMD-associated variants may exert site-specific effects (i.e. differ in the strength of their association and magnitude of effect across different skeletal sites). In particular, variants at CPED1 exerted a larger influence on SK-BMD and UL-BMD when compared to LL-BMD (P = 2.01 × 10(-37)), whilst variants at WNT16 influenced UL-BMD to a greater degree when compared to SK- and LL-BMD (P = 2.31 × 10(-14)). In addition, we report a novel association between RIN3 (previously associated with Paget's disease) and LL-BMD (rs754388: β = 0.13, SE = 0.02, P = 1.4 × 10(-10)). Our results suggest that BMD at different skeletal sites is under a mixture of shared and specific genetic and environmental influences. Allowing for these differences by performing genome-wide association at different skeletal sites may help uncover new genetic influences on BMD.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1371/journal.pgen.1004423</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>57</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Paternoster, Lavinia</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lorentzon, Mattias</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lehtimäki, Terho</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eriksson, Joel</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kähönen, Mika</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Raitakari, Olli</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Laaksonen, Marika</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sievänen, Harri</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Viikari, Jorma</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lyytikäinen, Leo-Pekka</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mellström, Dan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Karlsson, Magnus</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ljunggren, Osten</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Grundberg, Elin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kemp, John P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sayers, Adrian</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nethander, Maria</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Evans, David M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Vandenput, Liesbeth</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tobias, Jon H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohlsson, Claes</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2013</YEAR><TITLE>Genetic determinants of trabecular and cortical volumetric bone mineral densities and bone microstructure.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>PLoS genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>9</VOLUME><PAGES>e1003247</PAGES><ISBN>1553-7404</ISBN><LABEL>Paternoster2013</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Most previous genetic epidemiology studies within the field of osteoporosis have focused on the genetics of the complex trait areal bone mineral density (aBMD), not being able to differentiate genetic determinants of cortical volumetric BMD (vBMD), trabecular vBMD, and bone microstructural traits. The objective of this study was to separately identify genetic determinants of these bone traits as analysed by peripheral quantitative computed tomography (pQCT). Separate GWA meta-analyses for cortical and trabecular vBMDs were performed. The cortical vBMD GWA meta-analysis (n = 5,878) followed by replication (n = 1,052) identified genetic variants in four separate loci reaching genome-wide significance (RANKL, rs1021188, p = 3.6×10⁻¹⁴; LOC285735, rs271170, p = 2.7×10⁻¹²; OPG, rs7839059, p = 1.2×10⁻¹⁰; and ESR1/C6orf97, rs6909279, p = 1.1×10⁻⁹). The trabecular vBMD GWA meta-analysis (n = 2,500) followed by replication (n = 1,022) identified one locus reaching genome-wide significance (FMN2/GREM2, rs9287237, p = 1.9×10⁻⁹). High-resolution pQCT analyses, giving information about bone microstructure, were available in a subset of the GOOD cohort (n = 729). rs1021188 was significantly associated with cortical porosity while rs9287237 was significantly associated with trabecular bone fraction. The genetic variant in the FMN2/GREM2 locus was associated with fracture risk in the MrOS Sweden cohort (HR per extra T allele 0.75, 95% confidence interval 0.60-0.93) and GREM2 expression in human osteoblasts. In conclusion, five genetic loci associated with trabecular or cortical vBMD were identified. Two of these (FMN2/GREM2 and LOC285735) are novel bone-related loci, while the other three have previously been reported to be associated with aBMD. The genetic variants associated with cortical and trabecular bone parameters differed, underscoring the complexity of the genetics of bone parameters. We propose that a genetic variant in the RANKL locus influences cortical vBMD, at least partly, via effects on cortical porosity, and that a genetic variant in the FMN2/GREM2 locus influences GREM2 expression in osteoblasts and thereby trabecular number and thickness as well as fracture risk.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1371/journal.pgen.1003247</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>58</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Malaval, Luc</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wade-Guéye, Ndéyé Marième</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Boudiffa, Maya</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Fei, Jia</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zirngibl, Ralph</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chen, Frieda</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Laroche, Norbert</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Roux, Jean-Paul</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Burt-Pichat, Brigitte</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Duboeuf, François</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Boivin, Georges</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jurdic, Pierre</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lafage-Proust, Marie-Hélène</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Amédée, Joëlle</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Vico, Laurence</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rossant, Janet</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Aubin, Jane E</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2008</YEAR><DATE>May</DATE><TITLE>Bone sialoprotein plays a functional role in bone formation and osteoclastogenesis.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>The Journal of experimental medicine</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>205</VOLUME><PAGES>1145-1153</PAGES><ISBN>1540-9538</ISBN><LABEL>Malaval2008</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Bone sialoprotein (BSP) and osteopontin (OPN) are both highly expressed in bone, but their functional specificities are unknown. OPN knockout (-/-) mice do not lose bone in a model of hindlimb disuse (tail suspension), showing the importance of OPN in bone remodeling. We report that BSP(-/-) mice are viable and breed normally, but their weight and size are lower than wild-type (WT) mice. Bone is undermineralized in fetuses and young adults, but not in older (> or =12 mo) BSP(-/-) mice. At 4 mo, BSP(-/-) mice display thinner cortical bones than WT, but greater trabecular bone volume with very low bone formation rate, which indicates reduced resorption, as confirmed by lower osteoclast surfaces. Although the frequency of total colonies and committed osteoblast colonies is the same, fewer mineralized colonies expressing decreased levels of osteoblast markers form in BSP(-/-) versus WT bone marrow stromal cultures. BSP(-/-) hematopoietic progenitors form fewer osteoclasts, but their resorptive activity on dentin is normal. Tail-suspended BSP(-/-) mice lose bone in hindlimbs, as expected. In conclusion, BSP deficiency impairs bone growth and mineralization, concomitant with dramatically reduced bone formation. It does not, however, prevent the bone loss resulting from loss of mechanical stimulation, a phenotype that is clearly different from OPN(-/-) mice.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1084/jem.20071294</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>59</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Holmen, Sheri L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zylstra, Cassandra R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mukherjee, Aditi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sigler, Robert E</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Faugere, Marie-Claude</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bouxsein, Mary L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Deng, Lianfu</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Clemens, Thomas L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Williams, Bart O</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2005</YEAR><DATE>June</DATE><TITLE>Essential role of beta-catenin in postnatal bone acquisition.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>The Journal of biological chemistry</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>280</VOLUME><PAGES>21162-21168</PAGES><ISBN>0021-9258</ISBN><LABEL>Holmen2005</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Mutations in the Wnt co-receptor LRP5 alter bone mass in humans, but the mechanisms responsible for Wnts actions in bone are unclear. To investigate the role of the classical Wnt signaling pathway in osteogenesis, we generated mice lacking the beta-catenin or adenomatous polyposis coli (Apc) genes in osteoblasts. Loss of beta-catenin produced severe osteopenia with striking increases in osteoclasts, whereas constitutive activation of beta-catenin in the conditional Apc mutants resulted in dramatically increased bone deposition and a disappearance of osteoclasts. In vitro, osteoblasts lacking the beta-catenin gene exhibited impaired maturation and mineralization with elevated expression of the osteoclast differentiation factor, receptor activated by nuclear factor-kappaB ligand (RANKL), and diminished expression of the RANKL decoy receptor, osteoprotegerin. By contrast, Apc-deficient osteoblasts matured normally but demonstrated decreased expression of RANKL and increased osteoprotegerin. These findings suggest that Wnt/beta-catenin signaling in osteoblasts coordinates postnatal bone acquisition by controlling the differentiation and activity of both osteoblasts and osteoclasts.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1074/jbc.M501900200</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>60</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Kramer, Ina</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Baertschi, Stefan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Halleux, Christine</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Keller, Hansjoerg</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kneissel, Michaela</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2012</YEAR><DATE>February</DATE><TITLE>Mef2c deletion in osteocytes results in increased bone mass.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Journal of bone and mineral research : the official journal of the American Society for Bone and Mineral Research</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>27</VOLUME><PAGES>360-373</PAGES><ISBN>1523-4681</ISBN><LABEL>Kramer2012</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Myocyte enhancer factors 2 (MEF2) are required for expression of the osteocyte bone formation inhibitor Sost in vitro, implying these transcription factors in bone biology. Here, we analyzed the in vivo function of Mef2c in osteocytes in male and female mice during skeletal growth and aging. Dmp1-Cre-induced Mef2c deficiency led to progressive decreases in Sost expression by 40% and 70% in femoral cortical bone at 3.5 months and 5 to 6 months of age. From 2 to 3 months onward, bone mass was increased in the appendicular and axial skeleton of Mef2c mutant relative to control mice. Cortical thickness and long bone and vertebral trabecular density were elevated. To assess whether the increased bone mass was related to the decreased Sost expression, we characterized 4-month-old heterozygous Sost-deficient mice. Sost heterozygotes displayed similar increases in long bone mass and density as Mef2c mutants, but the relative increases in axial skeletal parameters were mostly smaller. At the cellular level, bone formation parameters were normal in 3.5-month-old Mef2c mutant mice, whereas bone resorption parameters were significantly decreased. Correspondingly, cortical expression of the anti-osteoclastogenic factor and Wnt/β-catenin target gene osteoprotegerin (OPG) was increased by 70% in Mef2c mutant males. Furthermore, cortical expression of the Wnt signaling modulators Sfrp2 and Sfrp3 was strongly deregulated in both sexes. In contrast, heterozygous Sost deficient males displayed mildly increased osteoblastic mineral apposition rate, but osteoclast surface and cortical expression of osteoclastogenic regulators including OPG were normal and Sfrp2 and Sfrp3 were not significantly changed. Together, our data demonstrate that Mef2c regulates cortical Sfrp2 and Sfrp3 expression and is required to maintain normal Sost expression in vivo. Yet, the increased bone mass phenotype of Mef2c mutants is not directly related to the reduced Sost expression. We identified a novel function for Mef2c in control of adult bone mass by regulation of osteoclastic bone resorption.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1002/jbmr.1492</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>61</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Simonet, W S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lacey, D L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dunstan, C R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kelley, M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chang, M S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lüthy, R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nguyen, H Q</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wooden, S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bennett, L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Boone, T</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Shimamoto, G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>DeRose, M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Elliott, R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Colombero, A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tan, H L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Trail, G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sullivan, J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Davy, E</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bucay, N</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Renshaw-Gegg, L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hughes, T M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hill, D</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pattison, W</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Campbell, P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sander, S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Van, G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tarpley, J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Derby, P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lee, R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Boyle, W J</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>1997</YEAR><DATE>April</DATE><TITLE>Osteoprotegerin: a novel secreted protein involved in the regulation of bone density.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Cell</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>89</VOLUME><PAGES>309-319</PAGES><ISBN>0092-8674</ISBN><LABEL>Simonet1997</LABEL><ABSTRACT>A novel secreted glycoprotein that regulates bone resorption has been identified. The protein, termed Osteoprotegerin (OPG), is a novel member of the TNF receptor superfamily. In vivo, hepatic expression of OPG in transgenic mice results in a profound yet nonlethal osteopetrosis, coincident with a decrease in later stages of osteoclast differentiation. These same effects are observed upon administration of recombinant OPG into normal mice. In vitro, osteoclast differentiation from precursor cells is blocked in a dose-dependent manner by recombinant OPG. Furthermore, OPG blocks ovariectomy-associated bone loss in rats. These data show that OPG can act as a soluble factor in the regulation of bone mass and imply a utility for OPG in the treatment of osteoporosis associated with increased osteoclast activity.</ABSTRACT></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>62</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Styrkarsdottir, Unnur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Halldorsson, Bjarni V</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gretarsdottir, Solveig</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gudbjartsson, Daniel F</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Walters, G Bragi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ingvarsson, Thorvaldur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jonsdottir, Thorbjorg</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Saemundsdottir, Jona</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Center, Jacqueline R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nguyen, Tuan V</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bagger, Yu</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gulcher, Jeffrey R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eisman, John A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Christiansen, Claus</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sigurdsson, Gunnar</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kong, Augustine</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Thorsteinsdottir, Unnur</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Stefansson, Kari</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2008</YEAR><DATE>May</DATE><TITLE>Multiple genetic loci for bone mineral density and fractures.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>The New England journal of medicine</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>358</VOLUME><PAGES>2355-2365</PAGES><ISBN>1533-4406</ISBN><LABEL>Styrkarsdottir2008</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Bone mineral density influences the risk of osteoporosis later in life and is useful in the evaluation of the risk of fracture. We aimed to identify sequence variants associated with bone mineral density and fracture. We performed a quantitative trait analysis of data from 5861 Icelandic subjects (the discovery set), testing for an association between 301,019 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and bone mineral density of the hip and lumbar spine. We then tested for an association between 74 SNPs (most of which were implicated in the discovery set) at 32 loci in replication sets of Icelandic, Danish, and Australian subjects (4165, 2269, and 1491 subjects, respectively). Sequence variants in five genomic regions were significantly associated with bone mineral density in the discovery set and were confirmed in the replication sets (combined P values, 1.2x10(-7) to 2.0x10(-21)). Three regions are close to or within genes previously shown to be important to the biologic characteristics of bone: the receptor activator of nuclear factor-kappaB ligand gene (RANKL) (chromosomal location, 13q14), the osteoprotegerin gene (OPG) (8q24), and the estrogen receptor 1 gene (ESR1) (6q25). The two other regions are close to the zinc finger and BTB domain containing 40 gene (ZBTB40) (1p36) and the major histocompatibility complex region (6p21). The 1p36, 8q24, and 6p21 loci were also associated with osteoporotic fractures, as were loci at 18q21, close to the receptor activator of the nuclear factor-kappaB gene (RANK), and loci at 2p16 and 11p11. We have discovered common sequence variants that are consistently associated with bone mineral density and with low-trauma fractures in three populations of European descent. Although these variants alone are not clinically useful in the prediction of risk to the individual person, they provide insight into the biochemical pathways underlying osteoporosis.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1056/NEJMoa0801197</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>63</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Antolic, Anamaria</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Roy, Brian D</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tarnopolsky, Mark A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zernicke, Ronald F</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wohl, Gregory R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Shaughnessy, Stephen G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bourgeois, Jacqueline M</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2007</YEAR><DATE>May</DATE><TITLE>Creatine monohydrate increases bone mineral density in young Sprague-Dawley rats.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Medicine and science in sports and exercise</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>39</VOLUME><PAGES>816-820</PAGES><ISBN>0195-9131</ISBN><LABEL>Antolic2007</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Creatine kinase, found in osteoblasts, is an enzyme that is upregulated in response to interventions that enhance bone mass accretion. Creatine monohydrate supplementation can increase fat-free mass in young healthy men and women and can reduce markers of bone breakdown in boys with Duchenne muscular dystrophy. The objective of this study was to determine the influence of supplementation with creatine monohydrate on bone structure and function in growing rats, to establish a therapeutic model. Creatine monohydrate (2% w.w.) (CR; N = 16) or standard rat chow (CON; N = 16) was fed to Sprague-Dawley rats beginning at 5 wk of age, for 8 wk. Bone mineral density (BMD) and content (BMC) were assessed using dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry at the beginning and end of the protocol. The rats were sacrificed, and one femur was removed for the determination of mechanical properties. The CR-treated rats showed greater lumbar BMD and femoral bending load at failure compared with the CON rats (P &#x3c; 0.05). Together, these data suggest that creatine monohydrate potentially has a beneficial influence on bone function and structure; further investigation is warranted into its effect on bone functional properties and its effects in disorders associated with bone loss.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1249/mss.0b013e318031fac4</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>64</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Huh, Ji Hye</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Choi, Soo In</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lim, Jung Soo</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chung, Choon Hee</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Shin, Jang Yel</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lee, Mi Young</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2015</YEAR><TITLE>Lower Serum Creatinine Is Associated with Low Bone Mineral Density in Subjects without Overt Nephropathy.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>PloS one</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>10</VOLUME><PAGES>e0133062</PAGES><ISBN>1932-6203</ISBN><LABEL>Huh2015</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Low skeletal muscle mass is associated with deterioration of bone mineral density. Because serum creatinine can serve as a marker of muscle mass, we evaluated the relationship between serum creatinine and bone mineral density in an older population with normal renal function. Data from a total of 8,648 participants (4,573 men and 4,075 postmenopausal women) aged 45-95 years with an estimated glomerular filtration rate >60 ml/min/1.73 m2 were analyzed from the Fourth Korea National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (2008-2010). Bone mineral density (BMD) and appendicular muscle mass (ASM) were measured using dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry. Receiver operating characteristic curve analysis revealed that the cut points of serum creatinine for sarcopenia were below 0.88 mg/dl in men and 0.75 mg/dl in women. Subjects were divided into two groups: low creatinine and upper normal creatinine according to the cut point value of serum creatinine for sarcopenia. In partial correlation analysis adjusted for age, serum creatinine was positively associated with both BMD and ASM. Subjects with low serum creatinine were at a higher risk for low BMD (T-score ≤ -1.0) at the femur neck, total hip and lumbar spine in men, and at the total hip and lumbar spine in women after adjustment for confounding factors. Each standard deviation increase in serum creatinine was significantly associated with reduction in the likelihood of low BMD at the total hip and lumbar spine in both sexes (men: odds ratio (OR) = 0.84 [95% CI = 0.74-0.96] at the total hip, OR = 0.8 [95% CI = 0.68-0.96] at the lumbar spine; women: OR = 0.83 [95% CI = 0.73-0.95] at the total hip, OR=0.81 [95% CI = 0.67-0.99] at the lumbar spine). Serum creatinine reflected muscle mass, and low serum creatinine was independently associated with low bone mineral density in subjects with normal kidney function.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1371/journal.pone.0133062</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>65</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Pattaro, Cristian</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>De Grandi, Alessandro</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Vitart, Veronique</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hayward, Caroline</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Franke, Andre</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Aulchenko, Yurii S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Johansson, Asa</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wild, Sarah H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Melville, Scott A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Isaacs, Aaron</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Polasek, Ozren</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ellinghaus, David</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kolcic, Ivana</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nöthlings, Ute</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zgaga, Lina</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zemunik, Tatijana</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gnewuch, Carsten</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Schreiber, Stefan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Campbell, Susan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hastie, Nick</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Boban, Mladen</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Meitinger, Thomas</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Oostra, Ben A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Riegler, Peter</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Minelli, Cosetta</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wright, Alan F</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Campbell, Harry</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van Duijn, Cornelia M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gyllensten, Ulf</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wilson, James F</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Krawczak, Michael</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Rudan, Igor</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pramstaller, Peter P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>consortium , EUROSPAN</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2010</YEAR><DATE>March</DATE><TITLE>A meta-analysis of genome-wide data from five European isolates reveals an association of COL22A1, SYT1, and GABRR2 with serum creatinine level.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>BMC medical genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>11</VOLUME><PAGES>41</PAGES><ISBN>1471-2350</ISBN><LABEL>Pattaro2010</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Serum creatinine (S CR) is the most important biomarker for a quick and non-invasive assessment of kidney function in population-based surveys. A substantial proportion of the inter-individual variability in S CR level is explicable by genetic factors. We performed a meta-analysis of genome-wide association studies of S CR undertaken in five population isolates ('discovery cohorts'), all of which are part of the European Special Population Network (EUROSPAN) project. Genes showing the strongest evidence for an association with SCR (candidate loci) were replicated in two additional population-based samples ('replication cohorts'). After the discovery meta-analysis, 29 loci were selected for replication. Association between SCR level and polymorphisms in the collagen type XXII alpha 1 (COL22A1) gene, on chromosome 8, and in the synaptotagmin-1 (SYT1) gene, on chromosome 12, were successfully replicated in the replication cohorts (p value = 1.0 x 10(-6) and 1.7 x 10(-4), respectively). Evidence of association was also found for polymorphisms in a locus including the gamma-aminobutyric acid receptor rho-2 (GABRR2) gene and the ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme E2-J1 (UBE2J1) gene (replication p value = 3.6 x 10(-3)). Previously reported findings, associating glomerular filtration rate with SNPs in the uromodulin (UMOD) gene and in the schroom family member 3 (SCHROOM3) gene were also replicated. While confirming earlier results, our study provides new insights in the understanding of the genetic basis of serum creatinine regulatory processes. In particular, the association with the genes SYT1 and GABRR2 corroborate previous findings that highlighted a possible role of the neurotransmitters GABAA receptors in the regulation of the glomerular basement membrane and a possible interaction between GABAA receptors and synaptotagmin-I at the podocyte level.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1186/1471-2350-11-41</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>66</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Chambers, John C</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zhang, Weihua</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lord, Graham M</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>van der Harst, Pim</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lawlor, Debbie A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sehmi, Joban S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gale, Daniel P</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wass, Mark N</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ahmadi, Kourosh R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bakker, Stephan J L</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Beckmann, Jacqui</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bilo, Henk J G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bochud, Murielle</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Brown, Morris J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Caulfield, Mark J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Connell, John M C</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cook, H Terence</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Cotlarciuc, Ioana</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Davey Smith, George</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>de Silva, Ranil</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Deng, Guohong</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Devuyst, Olivier</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dikkeschei, Lambert D</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dimkovic, Nada</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dockrell, Mark</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Dominiczak, Anna</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ebrahim, Shah</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Eggermann, Thomas</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Farrall, Martin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ferrucci, Luigi</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Floege, Jurgen</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Forouhi, Nita G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gansevoort, Ron T</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Han, Xijin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hedblad, Bo</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Homan van der Heide, Jaap J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hepkema, Bouke G</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hernandez-Fuentes, Maria</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hypponen, Elina</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Johnson, Toby</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>de Jong, Paul E</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kleefstra, Nanne</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lagou, Vasiliki</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lapsley, Marta</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Li, Yun</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Loos, Ruth J F</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Luan, Jian'an</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Luttropp, Karin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Maréchal, Céline</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Melander, Olle</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Munroe, Patricia B</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nordfors, Louise</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Parsa, Afshin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Peltonen, Leena</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Penninx, Brenda W</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Perucha, Esperanza</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pouta, Anneli</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Prokopenko, Inga</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Roderick, Paul J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ruokonen, Aimo</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Samani, Nilesh J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sanna, Serena</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Schalling, Martin</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Schlessinger, David</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Schlieper, Georg</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Seelen, Marc A J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Shuldiner, Alan R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sjögren, Marketa</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Smit, Johannes H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Snieder, Harold</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Soranzo, Nicole</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Spector, Timothy D</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Stenvinkel, Peter</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sternberg, Michael J E</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Swaminathan, Ramasamyiyer</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, Toshiko</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ubink-Veltmaat, Lielith J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Uda, Manuela</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Vollenweider, Peter</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wallace, Chris</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Waterworth, Dawn</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Zerres, Klaus</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Waeber, Gerard</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wareham, Nicholas J</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Maxwell, Patrick H</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>McCarthy, Mark I</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Jarvelin, Marjo-Riitta</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mooser, Vincent</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Abecasis, Goncalo R</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lightstone, Liz</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Scott, James</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Navis, Gerjan</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Elliott, Paul</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kooner, Jaspal S</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2010</YEAR><DATE>May</DATE><TITLE>Genetic loci influencing kidney function and chronic kidney disease.</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nature genetics</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>42</VOLUME><PAGES>373-375</PAGES><ISBN>1546-1718</ISBN><LABEL>Chambers2010</LABEL><ABSTRACT>Using genome-wide association, we identify common variants at 2p12-p13, 6q26, 17q23 and 19q13 associated with serum creatinine, a marker of kidney function (P = 10(-10) to 10(-15)). Of these, rs10206899 (near NAT8, 2p12-p13) and rs4805834 (near SLC7A9, 19q13) were also associated with chronic kidney disease (P = 5.0 x 10(-5) and P = 3.6 x 10(-4), respectively). Our findings provide insight into metabolic, solute and drug-transport pathways underlying susceptibility to chronic kidney disease.</ABSTRACT><URL>10.1038/ng.566</URL></RECORD>
<RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>13</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>67</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>R Core Team, </AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2015</YEAR><TITLE>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</TITLE><PLACE_PUBLISHED>Vienna, Austria</PLACE_PUBLISHED><LABEL>R-language</LABEL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>https://www.R-project.org/</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD>
</RECORDS></XML>

